Guide to the Stuart Wells Jackson Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Stuart Wells Jackson collection
1771-1949
MS 957
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.75
(2 boxes, 1 folio)
The major part of these papers consists of a collection of facsimilies of letters, documents, and memorabilia by and about Abraham Lincoln collected by Stuart Wells Jackson (1875-1957). Several items are original, among them holograph poems on Lincoln by William Cullen Bryant and Edwin Markham. There is also a small amount of Jackson's personal correspondence from 1902-1949.
Jackson, Stuart W. (Stuart Wells), 1875-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Stuart W. Jackson in the 1940s.
Scope and Contents
The Stuart Wells Jackson Collection consists of correspondence and other papers pertaining to Abraham Lincoln which were collected by Stuart W. Jackson. These include facsimiles of Lincoln correspondence, a deed signed by William Lincoln (1820 Feb 22), memorabilia, correspondence and writings about Lincoln, the 1861 diary of Joseph J. Williams, and other related items. These materials are arranged alphabetically by author and are listed in detail on the following page. There is, in addition, some personal correspondence of Stuart W. Jackson concerning his collection and research on Lincoln; these letters are also arranged alphabetically. While most of these letters were enclosed with writings which were sent to Jackson, and are generally routine, several are substantive. The letter from George P. Hambrecht (1924 May 6) encloses two short essays by Hambrecht, and the letter from Samuel B. Harding (1911 Oct 13) encloses typed copies of two Lincoln letters.
Finally, the collection contains several miscellaneous items, including membership certificates from three Lincoln societies and a photograph of Walt Whitman in 1890.
These papers were donated to Yale University by Stuart W. Jackson in the 1940s.
Biographical / Historical
Stuart Jackson has been president of Stuart W. Jackson, Inc., his insurance firm, since it was founded in 1915. He is president of Institut Français de Washington, the scope and purpose of which is to promote the study of French civilization, history, literature, and art in the United States. He is also president of the American Friends of Lafayette, whose principal object is to promote historical research dealing with the life and times of General Lafayette and French participation in the American Revolution. They publish and distribute such material. He is a trustee of the Yale Library Associates. He has contributed articles on Lafayette to several periodicals, and he compiled a Lafayette Bibliography with a preface by Whitlock and published in 1930 in a limited edition by William E. Rudge. He edited the May, 1934, Gazette published by Yale University Library—it was the Lafayette number, and the article was chiefly annotation of the Lafayette letters and documents in the library by or about J. Fenimore Cooper. In 1954 France gave him the decoration of Chevalier of the Legion of Honor.
He writes to an inquisitive Class secretary—i"It is very sweet of you to ask me to write a letter about myself during Prohibition and since. I'm really discouraged, however, that you do not seem to know what business I'm in after all these years, especially as you have intrusted to me some of your insurance needs for a long while. Really, Julien, I'm the best insurance broker in New York. The trouble is that not enough people seem to know it; otherwise, I could retire and play golf with you often. That's the only business anecdote I can send you now.
"You know damn well that I have not been blessed with children, and yet you beg me for their full names with their school and college careers. You then rub it in by inquiring about the health of my grandchildren.
"In closing I would like to say that you are my favorite Class secretary and even if you are a little personal at times I send my warm regards to you and '98. Avec bommage, S.W.J."
On November 4, 1905, he married Elizabeth Underwood Cox.
Stuart Wells Jackson died on November 21, 1957.
From Forty Years After: Class of 1898.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Diaries; Bryant, William Cullen, 1794-1878; Jackson, Stuart W. (Stuart Wells), 1875-; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865; Markham, Edwin, 1852-1940
- Inventory, 1771-1949; .75 linear feet (2 boxes)
  - Collected papers
    - Badger, M[ilton, 1800-1873?]: ALS to Rev. Joshua Leavitt, 1857 October 30 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bryant, William Cullen: AMS of poem, "Abraham Lincoln", 1865 April (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Conant, Alban Joseph: statement re his portrait of Lincoln, 1911 March 15 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Douglas, Benjamin: ALS (copy by BD) to Abraham Lincoln, 1860 December 26 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Duer, William: ALS (photostatic copy) to Francis Lightfoot Lee, 1788 February 14 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Gordon, James: ALS to Mildred L. Rutherford, with pamphlet by Mildred L. Rutherford, 1894 August 11 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Lafayette, Marie, marquis de: ALS (photostatic copy) to John Adams, 1786 February 26 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Lincoln Abraham
      - ALS (facsimile) to Grace Bedell, 1860 October 19 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - AL (facsimile) to Benjamin F. Butler, signed by Edwin M. Stanton, [1864 January 18] (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - ALS (facsimile) to William M. Dickson, 1865 February 27 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - ALS (forgery) to Ninian W. Edwards, 1845 December 12 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - ALS (facsimile) to the parents of Ephraim E. Ellsworth, with photographs and memorabilia, 1861 May 25 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - ALS (facsimile) to John J. Hardin, 1844 December 17, 1846 May 29 (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
      - ALS (facsimile) to Samuel Haycroft, 1860 May 28 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - ALS (facsimile) to Philip Kearny, 1861 October 2 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - ALS (facsimile) to Richard P. Morgan, 1856 February 13 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - ALS (facsimile) to George D. Ramsay, 1861 October 17 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - ALS (photostatic copy) to Joshua F. Speed, with typed copy of letter of Speed to Lincoln, 1860 May 19, 22 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - ALS (photostatic copy) to Edwin M. Stanton, 1862 September 2 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - ALS (photostatic copy) [probably to Rev. Robert Pott and associates] concerning the work of the Methodist Episcopal Church in the Civil War, 1864 May 18 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - ALS (photographic negative and electrostatic copy) to whom it may concern, 1861 October 4 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - DS in the hand of Lincoln, signed Stuart and Lincoln, 1839 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - List of depositions of court cases in Sangamon County, [1846?] (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - Pocket notebook (facsimile) for the campaign of 1858, 1858 October 18 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Emancipation Proclamation (facsimile), 1862 September 22 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - Gettysburg Address (photostatic copy), 1863 November 19 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Lincoln, William: deed relating to land in Granville, Ohio, 1820 February 22 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Lincoln Memorial: dedication booklet autographed by Warren G. Harding, William H. Taft, Daniel Chester French, James Guerin, and Robert R. Moton, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Markham, Edwin: AMS of poem, "Lincoln the Man of People", 1927 December (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - New York (State) Legislature: petition by members of the Legislature for appointment of Chauncey Shaffer as U.S. District Attorney, endorsed by Lincoln, [1860-1861?] (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Pickering, William: ALS (photostatic copy) to Issac N. Arnold, with ALS (photostatic copy) from Lincoln to a friend, 1864 February 23, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Rhinelander, Walton: 4 ALS to his sister Till, 1861 May-June (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Ropes, John Codman: ALS to H.B. Dawson, 1877 August 24 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Schurz, Carl: autograph, 1897 February 5 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Sours, A.L.: ANS to [C.?] H. Hart, 1867 February 25 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Williams, Joseph J.: diary, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Wills, David: affidavit relating to Lincoln's, composition of the Gettysburg Address, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Miscellaneous clippings and writings about Lincoln, 1909, 1917, undated (Box 1, Folder 38A)
    - Political ribbons, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Printed likenesses of Lincoln, undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Personal papers, 1902-1949
    - Correpondence
      - A-B (Box 1, Folder 41)
      - C-Y (Box 2, Folder 42-48)
    - Miscellaneous papers (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Indenture, signed by William Alexander, Earl of Stirling, John Reid, et al. (photostatic copy), 1771 April 27 (Box 3)
  - "A Resolution submitting to the legislature of the several states a proposition to amend the Constitution of the United States" (facsimile), 1864 December 5 (Box 3)
  - Portrait of Lincoln, undated (Box 3)
  - Portrait of David Wills, undated